Guide to the Belmont Mercer Farley Papers, 1787-1965, 2015 RL.00380
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Belmont Mercer Farley papers
1787-1965, 2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Farley, Belmont Mercer
RL.00380
27.0 Linear Feet
Educator from Washington, D.C. Professional papers concern academic freedom, educational television, reading and illiteracy, rural education, attacks on textbooks, federal aid to education, school construction, and strikes. Also discussed are the Ford Foundation, American anti-communist sentiment, peace and war, the U.S. military, and the atomic bomb. There is extensive material on the National Education Association, particularly on public relations and the advent of American educational broadcasting. Also included are Farley's articles, addresses, and radio program scripts, all of which regard U.S. public schools, and material pertaining to educational organization conventions that Farley attended. Personal papers chiefly consist of letters on family genealogy, with some information on public education in Missouri and California, and detailed notes and a self-published 381-page book on the family genealogy, which includes many other families in addition to the Farleys and Mercers.
Approximately 19,767 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Belmont Mercer Farley Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1968 and gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
Belmont Farley's professional papers span his career as an educator, author, and staff member with the National Education Association, and concern academic freedom, educational television, reading and illiteracy, rural education, attacks on textbooks, federal aid to education, school construction, and strikes. Also discussed are the Ford Foundation, American anti-communist sentiment, peace and war, the U.S. military, and the atomic bomb. There is extensive material on the National Education Association, particularly on public relations and the advent of American educational broadcasting. Also included are Farley's articles, addresses, and radio program scripts, all of which regard U.S. public schools, and material pertaining to educational organization conventions that Farley attended.
Personal papers chiefly consist of letters exchanged between Farley and family members on family genealogy, with some information on public education in Missouri and California. There are also detailed notes and a self-published 381-page genealogy of the Farley-Mercer families, which stretches from Pensylvania, Maryland, North Carolina, Missouri, and other states, and offers detailed information on the Musser, Metzgar, Gosser, Greenlee, Youngs, Guarco, Dyer, Spangler, Cleland, Carr (Kerr), and Dinsmore families. This book was published in 1932, and updated and republished by Farley's son Thomas Farley in 2015.
Biographical note
Belmont Mercer Farley (1891-1975) was born in Missouri and began his career as a teacher and school superintendent. He then joined the Washington, D.C.-based National Education Association, working from 1929 until his retirement in 1956 in the divisions of NEA publications and public relations. He was especially active on behalf of educational broadcasting during FCC hearings in the early 1950s. In the 1920s, he researched the history of the Farley-Mercer families back to the 18th century, publishing a genealogy in 1932, which was updated and republished by his son in 2015. Farley Mercer died in April 1975.
Academic freedom -- United States; Anti-communist movements -- United States; Education -- United States; Education -- Political aspects -- United States; Educators -- Correspondence; Educators -- United States; Federal aid to education; Literacy -- United States; Maryland -- Genealogy; Missouri -- Genealogy; North Carolina -- Genealogy; Pennsylvania -- Genealogy; Scrapbooks; National Educational Association (U.S.); Farley family; Mercer family
- Correspondence, 1901-1965, 15 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Farley's professional correspondence contains letters from school superintendents as well as college professors and presidents, such as Rollo G. Reynolds, Fred Engelhardt, Uel W. Lamkin, Florence Hale, Thomas W. Nadal, Willis A. Sutton, and Eldo L. Hendricks. Persons prominent in the National Education Association, such as Willard E. Givens and William G. Carr, also corresponded with Farley, as well as the editors Bernard L. Johnson and Frank A. Weld; the Commissioner of the Federal Communications Commission Frieda B. Hennock; George H. Adams, a newspaper reporter; and Franklin D. Roosevelt's son James.
  Since Farley kept in close touch with relatives, there are a large number of family letters in the personal correspondence, the bulk of which begins in the 1920s. His brother Paul's letters contain some information on public education in Missouri and California.
  - Genealogical, 1930-1959
    - 1930-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1959 (Box 3)
  - Personal, 1901-1965
    - 1901-1921 (Box 3)
    - 1922-1931 July (Box 4)
    - 1931 Aug.-1934 Aug. (Box 5)
    - 1935-1940 (Box 6)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 7)
    - 1944-1948 (Box 8)
    - 1949-1953 (Box 9)
    - 1954-1956 Aug. (Box 10)
    - 1956 Sept.-1959 June (Box 11)
    - 1959 July-1961 (Box 12)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 13)
  - Professional, 1925-1936 (Box 14)
  - Professional, 1937-1959 (Box 15)
- Financial and Legal Papers, 3 boxes
  - Legal Papers (Box 15-16)
  - Financial Papers (Box 17)
- Subject Files, 20 boxes
  Organized in original alphabetical file order.
  - A-Annual Reports (Box 17)
  - Anti-Federal Aid to Education-Aviation (Box 18)
  - B-Cartoons (Box 19)
  - Church-Communism Charges (Box 20)
  - Conference-Education (Box 21)
  - Education-Freedom (Box 22)
  - Friends-H (Box 23)
  - I-JCET (Box 24)
  - JCET-Minneapolis (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous-Missouri (Box 26)
  - Missouri-Opposition (Box 27)
  - Outline-Public (Box 28)
  - Public-Quotation (Box 29)
  - Reading-Russian (Box 30)
  - S-Scrapbook (Box 31)
  - Sears-Teacher (Box 32)
  - Teacher-Tributes (Box 33)
  - U-University (Box 34)
  - University-V (Box 35)
  - W-Z (Box 36)
- Genealogy, 3 boxes
  - Genealogical materials, 3 boxes (Box 39-41)
  - Farley-Mercer family records, by Belmont Farley, 1932, updated by Thomas Farley, 2015, 1 volume, 381 pages (Box 69)
- Printed Material, 3 boxes
  - Clippings (Box 18)
  - Printed Material (Box 39-40)
- Professional Papers, 29 boxes
  - Dissertation manuscript (Box 40)
  - Addresses (Box 41)
  - Writings (Box 41)
  - Press releases (Box 42)
  - Our American Schools, draft (Box 42)
  - Memoirs of a Journey, Vol. II (Box 43)
  - Volumes (Box 43)
  - Meetings and reunions (Box 44)
  - Articles and pamphlets (Box 45)
  - Meetings (Box 45-46)
  - Meetings and conferences, Washington D.C. (Box 47)
  - Meetings and conferences (Box 48)
  - Articles and addresses (Box 48)
  - Conventions (Box 49-51)
  - Articles and addresses (Box 51-67)
  - Scrapbook, 1937 (Volume F:806)
  - Volume: dissertation (Box 68)
  - Oversize items (Oversize-folder OF1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Consists of black-and-white photographs; certificate for lifetime membership in the National Education Association; elementary education teaching certificate; and a diploma from Taylor University.